howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to jim
rut show com that's Jim rut show com
today's guest is John Koza founder of
national popular vote Inc good morning
Jim it's great to be here great to have
you on John you know I don't know how
long we've known each other but it's
been quite a while and great to have you
on the Jim Rutz show for those who don't
know John he has one of the most
incredible resumes of anybody I've known
in fact maybe the most incredible back
in 1973 he founded Scientific Games Inc
the inventor of the scratch off lottery
ticket which was introduced in the 1970s
in fact I remember the great hoop lob
round it when it was introduced in
Maryland in 1976 I was working at a car
dealership and I can recall all the
other car salesmen other than me never
found the dumbass gambling attractive
we're like utterly sucked into this
stuff they were constantly dashing
across the street to the local liquor
store to buy more scratch off lottery
tickets and that was a huge success
needless to say we go to any convenience
store in most states we see racks and
racks and racks of these scratch off
lottery tickets that was John's
invention next in the 1980s John
invented genetic programming basically
the application of genetic computation
to the evolution of computer code this
was again another huge and seminal
invention which is in widespread use
today to chip design software companies
I helped launch use genetic program near
the core of their products and both of
those companies were successful third
and I don't want to say finally because
who knows what John will come up with
next in 2006 John launched national
popular vote an audacious move to
replace the electoral college in
presidential elections without requiring
amending of the Constitution
let's now jump in with the first John
won't you tell us a little bit about the
scratch off lottery ticket how did you
come up with that idea well while I was
a graduate student at the University of
Michigan in the 1960s I had a part-time
job doing computer programming for a
company that made commercial promotional
games the kind of games that were run at
the time of in gas stations and
supermarkets to increase sales and one
of the categories of games they had were
called probability games and these were
game tickets where the customer would
only rub off a subset of the number of
rub off spots on the ticket maybe three
out of 12 and if the right symbols were
under the three spots that the customer
chose they would win a prize these were
called probability games because every
single ticket was a potential winner of
perhaps $100 so the tickets obviously
had to have a secure covering and that
was a technology it existed at the time
but more importantly if you were
offering $100 in each ticket savvy
customers and in particular savvy clerks
in the gas stations and supermarkets
might be able to find the winning spots
on tickets by looking at little printing
irregularities that existed on the
tickets so there was a problem of how do
I make these tickets secure though that
you could offer a prize perhaps $100
cash on every ticket and do so safely
without causing the supermarket or gas
station to go bankrupt
okay had that been lead to the lottery
ticket well we did successfully produce
these probability games for commercial
clients in the late 60s and early 70s
and we did so securely and we did it by
printing roughly a half a million
different ticket combinations so that if
you rub the first spot even if there was
a printing irregularity on the exterior
or the under the spot that a person
might notice
would be d correlated with what was on
other spots on the ticket and the way we
did that is if there were 12 spots on
the ticket
we might print four of the spots on one
pass and this is at a time when you were
printing tickets on big sheets
lithographically you might have ten
different kinds of sheets each would say
a hundred tickets so you'd have a
thousand different patterns that would
not be sufficient to provide security
because if you had a given symbol under
a given spot a thousand is simply not
enough to D correlate with what's on the
other spot so then we would take these
big stacks of sheets and ten stacks we'd
collate the sheets one by one and then
print ten more print four spots each on
each of the thousand tickets so that now
there were eight of the twelve spots and
then we would again gather up the sheets
one by one and do it a third time so
that we would get roughly 1/2 million
different combinations of tickets and in
particularly there'd be no correlation
between a East spot that you might
uncover with one rub and where that
desirable second and third symbol would
be on the ticket so we're able to
produce a secure game that offered a
very substantial prize that I'm a
hundred dollars on each and every ticket
and do so securely now what does that
have to do with state lotteries well the
state lotteries were just getting
started in the 60s there were just a
handful of them and they were all
running rather uninteresting raffle type
games where they would print tickets
with say a six digit number and once a
week they hold a drawing and if you
match the number or part of the number
you went a prize so there was no
immediate gratification there was no
particular excitement or artistic ness
or attractiveness to the tickets and
sales were languishing in all the state
lotteries so we had the idea when I was
work
for this commercial game company of
saying well if the state lotteries could
have an instant gratification use this
rub off technology and all those states
would not want to run a probability game
that would would have been much too
risky for a state government to
undertake we could take this super
secure technology that was good enough
to offer a substantial price on every
ticket and run a controlled game where
the winners were predetermined and
pre-printed and again successfully
prevent any clerk in a store from
finding the winning tickets plucking
them out so that the consuming public
wouldn't beginning the winners so we
saddled was called the agent pick on a
problem for control games which is could
the clerk's who were selling the tickets
in these hundreds of convenience stores
around the state so that they couldn't
pick out the winning tickets though I do
remember in Maryland again my home state
there was a big scandal because it
turned out there was a way to do it
which was that the winning tickets were
slightly smaller than the non winning
tickets I don't know if they were
printed separately before they were
mixed in or what and there was a gang of
criminals that went around to all the
convenience stores and all the liquor
stores and paid the clerk some amount of
money to go through the tickets and
measure them and were able to pull out
the winners so there was at least one
way somebody did hack that particular
problem of course they fixed that but an
example of how smart adversarial agents
were that was of course a commercial
gain out of the state lottery there was
never an incidence of successful pick
out in a state lottery no that was the
scratch-off Maryland State Lottery they
were able to hack it based on the sides
of card I do recall that quite vividly I
believe it was probably in the late 70s
maybe early eighties well they fixed it
it was you know probably a problem where
they're having imprinted into different
printers and the size of stock was just
slightly smaller on the winners but
anyway so you developed this technology
so that no one could get through the
print or at least out of the the cover
thing though I imagine you could
probably do it with electro
microscope or something but not
worthwhile to do it a clerk ripoff level
how did that then turn into a company
and how did you convince the states to
do this well because we did have a
secure method of printing the tickets
and I don't know what you remember but I
can assure you none of the tickets
produced by scientific games had ever
been compromised in that fashion
perhaps they ran a game with somebody
else that I was aware of but we had a
method to securely print the tickets so
that there would be no agent picked out
and we first convinced the Massachusetts
lottery to run an instant lottery which
was a very big step at the time because
they were introducing a new type of game
with this potential agent pick out
problem and they did that in the spring
of 1974 it was immediately very
successful tripled the sales of the
Massachusetts lottery and every
subsequent lottery that adopted it and
that was the beginning of our company
scientific games our business was
selling instant lottery tickets to state
lotteries cool and did you guys
basically own that business or was it
what do you have competitors well when
we started we were actually the fifth
company to get the contract from the
Massachusetts Lottery to run their
instant game but each of the previous
four companies that got the contract
which included some very well-known now
banknote printing companies each of them
when they printed the sample tickets for
the lottery the lottery was able to
compromise the tickets from the
contracts were cancelled so we were the
fifth company to get a contract and we
successfully printed a secured ticket
and got it on the street and produced
the commercial success and from that we
went to all the other states at the time
and offered the instant lottery and of
course the state lotteries were quite
anxious to start running the instant
lottery yeah and as you say they're big
big business for the states today what
do you think of the morality of things
like that
I've read fair amount that says that you
know the use of these kinds particularly
the scratch-off lottery is inversely
proportional to people's incomes well I
haven't been about in the lottery
business for thirty years but it was
definitely not the case when I was there
in fact we did the extensive marketing
studies Danskin lottery had a actually
higher income profile than lotteries in
general that is the raffle type lottery
or the lotto games that came along
mainly because the ticket was a more
expensive ticket it was a dollar ticket
at the time whereas other lottery ticket
were fifty cents so at least at the time
when I was involved in the business
which was until the late eighties the
demographics of the incident ticket was
distinctly not lower income it was
distinctly middle income okay well
that's good well that's enough on the
lottery again an amazing insight and
innovation and invention and then take
the market with high quality let's move
next to genetic programming as I
understand it you were a student of John
Holland's who's one of my heroes fact
his book adaptation and natural and
artificial systems was the first book
that I read in the area of evolutionary
computation and it drew me into working
in that area and then eventually into
the area of complex science maybe you
start a little bit with your work with
John Holland and then how that led to
genetic programming well again while I
was a student of John Holland's in the
late 60s and early 70s in the computer
science department at the University of
Michigan and he was my thesis advisor he
had invented the genetic algorithms in
the mid 60s
which is an evolutionary computation
technique that is useful for solving a
lot of engineering and optimization
problems in an automated way and it's a
matter of fact as I was a graduate
student working on their PhD thesis that
was at the same time I was doing the
part-time consulting for the game
company that was producing the
probability games in any case I I had
gotten interested in the notion of
automatically
ramming computers to solve problems in
1963 I was in John Holland's one of his
courses I was an undergraduate at the
time and he had of course I'm adaptive
systems and one of the papers we read
was freiburg's paper on trying to have a
computer automatically learn how to
program itself to solve a problem and
that was through a mutational method and
I was very taken by that idea at the
time and my eventual PhD thesis was
somewhat related to that it was not
actually a thesis on genetic programming
it was attempted algorithm to infer
grammar from data but inferring a
grammar from data it can be seen as a
way of writing a computer program in any
case my thesis was sort of inspired from
the field of genetic algorithms even
though it wasn't in the field of genetic
algorithms and it was inspired by this
idea of trying to get computers to
program themselves even though it wasn't
exactly that so from somewhere around
1976 right when John Holland's book came
out and I was in the lottery business at
the time and quite busy running around
selling tickets to state lotteries I did
buy a copy of his book right when it
came out and as you were influenced by
it so was I very good it's interesting
for our audience if you could go into
the basics a little bit just Vicki but
very basic that we have a well-educated
audience but not experts in either
computer science or genetic or
evolutionary algorithms how do genetic
algorithms work and then how was that
idea extended to genetic programming
well the idea that genetic algorithm is
a vaguely patterned after the notion of
DNA that is you have a linear string of
symbols with DNA it's four symbols in
the classic simplest form of the genetic
algorithm the string is just a binary
string of ones and zeros and those ones
and zeros mean something in relation to
some problem for
the first few symbols might together
specify the size of an insect swing and
maybe the next few symbols might specify
the body color and maybe the next ones
would be the type of clawed insect has
etc so that the idea of the genetic
algorithm was that there would be a
string of ones and zeros that would
represent something in the real world
something perhaps you were trying to
optimize and you would do the
optimization in the following way first
of all you would create a random
population of these strings of ones and
zeros maybe a thousand strings of length
of say 50 and totally at random and then
you would look at each of these random
thousand individuals and say how good
are these insects of doing whatever
they're supposed to be doing maybe
foraging and getting fat on the food to
eat so you would assign a fitness to
each of these thousand randomly chosen
strings fitness being how good are the
things that these strings represent it's
solving the problem at hand which is say
getting fat I'm happy that creates a
population with Fitness which is
somewhat similar to the Darwinian notion
of natural selection and then the notion
of the genetic algorithm is you start
with the random population of
individuals and you modify that
population and create a new generation
with a small part of that thousand maybe
10% you just do a random mutation where
you flip one of the bits from 0 to 1 or
1 to 0 and that would correspond to a
random mutation say of a DNA string the
same sort of random mutation where if it
happens at the wrong place can make the
difference between having sickle-cell
anemia because of having defective
hemoglobin are not having sickle-cell
anemia or cystic for a process or not
having cystic fibrosis so mutation is a
way to
lately improve a given individual by
making a very small very localized
change and that notion of breeding a
population of binary strings have been
floating around since the late 40s
actually one of the first computer runs
on the computer that they had at the
Center for Advanced Studies at Princeton
was a simple genetic algorithm run made
him I believe the late forties but what
Holland added was the notion that the
real engine of creation in nature and
evolution is sexual reproduction where a
major part of the genome this string of
length 50 comes from one parent the
other part of the string comes from
another parent and this is roughly
analogous to the way sexual reproduction
occurs in simple genomes okay and that
would be the bulk of the transformation
that creates the new generation so maybe
10% might be a mere copying based on
reproduction and or some mutation but
maybe 90% or 80% would be crossover that
is the sexual recombination where you
take a major part of the genome of one
individual and you made it with a major
part of the genome of a second
individual creating an offspring that
has a major number of characteristics
from the father and a major number of
characteristics from the mother so that
takes us from the initial read of
generation to the first generation and
then the essence of the genetic
algorithm is to go through many many
generations maybe hundreds of
generations or thousands and constantly
refine the population based on a bit of
just straight reproduction copying
individual proportion we based on their
fitness a tiny bit of mutation again
selecting the individuals proportionate
to their fitness but then a major
portion of population being shuffled
around in this
very disruptive way called crossover to
produce new individuals and it turns out
you can solve a whole bunch of very
interesting engineering optimization
problems by using the genetic algorithm
as well as a whole variety of other
problems yeah that's quite remarkable I
remember when I first started writing
evolutionary computation you know you'd
go holy moley I do nothing at all other
than set up this environment and
evolution itself drives the solution and
for lots as you say many many problems
it works sometimes it works very slowly
I would often describe genetic
algorithms or my own particular variant
which was neural nets encoded as genetic
algorithms back in 2001 I'd say it's a
very general method but a very weak one
and that it takes a very long time and a
lot of computation to converge on a
solution at least for a difficult
problem I'd also like to highlight for
our audience the key factor you
mentioned it a couple of times I
mentioned it again which is that these
parents for the sexual reproduction of
these genomes are selected in some
fashion that's proportionate to their
fitness now there's lots of different
algorithms by which one may choose to
select all right you might do rank order
you might do weighted strength you know
actually how strong the thing was
relative to the alternative you might do
tournament selection this is actually
one I tended to use a lot which is I
grabbed for parents have each of them
play against each other and then the
winner of each of those would reproduce
and there are many many different ways
to tune that proportional selection for
reproduction and it turns out how you
tune it tends to impact how quickly the
genetic algorithm will converge towards
a good answer now there is no right
answer to all that from an important
theorem which we discussed before on
this show that no free lunch theorem
there's no best way for all problems
which is you know one of the challenges
of these techniques is that the tunings
the meta settings for evolutionary
algorithms you can make some good
guesses but at some level they're
they're trial and error to get those
things set correctly
so that's the genetic algorithm could
you explain to us how you extended the
idea of genetic algorithm to the genetic
program well as I said I got Holland's
book in 1976 but I was the founder and
CEO of a company that I was running at
the time to someone lottery tickets to
state governments so I was quite busy
and I was sort of followed Pelham's
achievements with the genetic algorithm
and all the other people who at the idea
and refined it and introduced all the
technique Jim that you were just talking
about different variations and ways of
doing it but I was involved in the
lottery business till 87 between 1973
and 87 and this sort of an academic
interest of mine to be watching what was
going on in this new field of genetic
algorithms so I left the lottery
business in 87 and at that point I was
as involved a little in venture capital
but I got involved with some people in
Stanford University in the computer
science department and got to talking to
them about genetic algorithms and said
well wouldn't it be nice that there was
a course at Stanford University on
genetic algorithms so they appointed me
as a consulting a faculty member
ultimately a consulting professor and I
started teaching a course at Stanford
starting in 88 which was just about the
time when the genetic algorithm field
was really starting to take off and
started to have conferences and public
proceedings and lots of papers as
opposed to one or two papers a year
there would be you know a hundred papers
a year in this growing field of genetic
algorithms and of course what motivated
me was still this memory of Freiburg's
paper that I ran into in 1963 which was
the notion that you could have a
computer program itself mm now
Freiburg's
work was with binary strings and you
could quickly see that by next
not a particularly expressive way to
deal with a problem like this so I said
why couldn't we apply the genetic
algorithm to pull computer programs and
in particular hold computer programs in
lits which was simply a functional
programming or tree like representation
of program so if you're doing an
addiction you have a function addition
and two arguments and you add them
together and if one of those arguments
do adding together was the product that
stay multiplying two other numbers you
would have this tree of operations so
you can represent computer programs in
functional programming languages as
program trees and the interesting thing
about program trees is that
automatically suggest to you the idea of
regarding a portion of a large program
tree as part of a genome and if the
program tree is just a little good at
solving a problem and you've got another
program tree over here that's just a
little good at solving that same problem
and you took a big chunk of one program
tree from the father and another chunk
of the program tree from the mother and
you swapped those sub trees in effect
you would be doing something like the
genetic algorithm does when it takes a
portion of a binary string but you'd be
taking a coherent chunk of computer
program and that's the notion behind
genetic programming namely you start now
with a population of a thousand randomly
created binary strings of length 50 but
you start out with a thousand computer
programs each of which is a program tree
containing multiplication and addition
and conditional operations and maybe
some cosines and Exponential's and some
other things and you ask how good is
this program at solving the problem you
have
how good is at doing a sorting algorithm
how good is it at creating a polynomial
that matches a given sample of data
maybe the stock market data how good is
this program at controlling the
operation of a robot if the operations
in the program are say moving forward
and turning and moving backwards and
reaching out and so forth so what you
get by moving into the world of computer
programs instead of binary strings is a
much greater richness of expressiveness
because you can have operations that are
much more meaningful
addition/subtraction
move the robot forward shuffle the
things if you're trying to develop a
sorting algorithm and so forth the
individual no population would be much
more expressive and somehow it
intuitively makes sense that if this
program is somewhat good at solving the
problem when this other program is
somewhat good maybe if you cross over to
the sexual recombination of part of one
good program and part of another program
and do it enough times that you'll get a
offspring that's better than either of
the parents at solving the problem and
that's the essence of genetic
programming you start with the random
population of computer programs you run
the program see how good they are at
solving the problems based on their
fitness it solving the problems you do a
small amount of mutation at very small
one or two percent a bit of reproduction
maybe 10 percent and then you with 90
percent of the population you do these
crossovers where you take a big chunk of
one program and cross it over with a big
chunk of another program and see if you
get something better and it turns out
you can solve just an enormous variety
of problems with this genetic
programming technique whether they're
data matching programs with we call
symbolic regression or control problems
of controlling a robot to do something
or controller and the
sense of a you know a PID controller or
whether it's an electrical serpent is
this a good filter circuit is this a
good amplifier is this a good
temperature sensing circuit etc turns
out you can evolve computer programs
that salvo just a wide variety of
problems in optical lens design
controller design antenna design data
matching robot control 13 algorithms a
number of people worked on quantum
computing algorithms that they evolved
with genetic programming and just a vast
variety of problems yeah I'm always
amazed when I see the ever-growing list
of things that genetic programming can
be applied to I mean what I remember
from the relatively early days I think I
actually saw you present on this at
Gecko was that you had had your genetic
programming environments had discovered
some analog circuits that had actually
been patented could you talk about that
a little bit well yes so one of my
things that interested me of course was
doing what I would call the aim of
course was to create some human
competitive results with genetic
programming and one of the categories
we've worked on a lot was analog circuit
design now there are all sorts of
algorithms for digital circuit designs
but analog circuit design is an art as
is antenna design and controller design
and frankly most engineering design
problems are matter of art as well as
mathematics and science so we said could
we use this to automatically create
analog electrical circuits that was one
of the big projects we worked on and
obviously you could use it on digital
circuits that was quite straightforward
but and the idea there was we we went
back through the patent literature from
the early 1910s and 20s when telephones
was the leading technology and things
like filters and amplifiers and feedback
were big issues and we started saying
well suppose we had a bunch of resistors
and capacitors and inductors which is
what the
at that time period and telephones could
you get an automated process that would
just combine these common ingredients to
produce circuits well what's the
filtered well a loaf of pass filter is
like the woofer on your hi-fi you know
passes the low frequency signals through
it freely and it suppresses the high
frequency signal well it turns out if
you create a random population of
circuits and ask how good are these
circuits at filtering a signal you can
easily compute the fitness and see how
well does it pass say frequencies from
zero to a thousand and how well does it
suppress frequencies from a thousand and
above so you can compute fitness and
then you can start slightly mutating a
few and reproducing a few but more
importantly crossing over circuits that
just do a little well at filtering with
each other and lo and behold we started
evolving the Campbell filter which is
the classic bladder filter of inductors
and capacitors that was patented I think
in 1917 if I recall and then of course
there are all sorts of improved filters
the Butterworth filters and the
elliptical filters and the power filters
and the M derived filters and so forth
there's a whole johnson filters there
are a whole variety of filters that had
particular additional characteristics
they were very good at creating a steep
fall off or this or that or more in ten
uation or what-have-you and we were able
to reproduce about a half dozen of the
filtered patents of the 1920s and 30s up
including the elliptic filter which is
an essentially one of the most
complicated ones using genetic
programming and then we got involved
with all kinds of other circuits who
said well transistors were invented at
the late forties and early fifties why
don't we throw in transistors as well as
resistors and capacitors and lo and
behold we started being able to evolve
things that were patented in the 50s 60s
and 70s with transistors that is
significant inventions not just novelty
toy circuits and then what you may have
heard that gecko was after the new
millennium rock we found six patented
circuits that have been patented by
different universities or big companies
and we were able to recreate a circuit
that performed as well or better than
the patented circuit in six specific
cases and in one of the specific cases
the genetically valve circuit was
essentially the patented circuit in five
of the six the circuit was equivalent in
performance the patented circuit but
quite different in the way it solves the
problem which is to say we were
genetically evolving circuits that would
avoid infringing the patented circuit so
not only were reinventing things that
were considered significant inventions
by universities or companies at the time
and worthy of patents but we were
duplicating patents and creating a
method to essentially avoid infringing
existing patents by creating equivalent
circuits but then we played the same
game with optics now I had taken one
Electrical Engineering course when I was
graduating so I was I'm not an
electrical engineer but I knew just a
little about Electrical Engineering knew
absolutely nothing about optics and with
help of several programmers who also
knew nothing about optics we were able
to duplicate six 21st century optical
pens that is we're able to genetically
evolve a lens system that equaled or
exceeded the performance of six lens
systems that have been tended by big
companies in the optical field so we
demonstrated that this process now
he worked in a important area electrical
engineering but also in a another area
where we could go into it with no
particular expertise of our own about
land systems that simply apply this
domain independent well-established
well-defined mechanical method and
duplicate patents and we duplicated some
antennas antenna patents and the
controller patents and other people of
course who've worked on this have
created all sorts of interesting other
inventions of quantum computer circuit
programs and many other things yeah and
again just an underline for our audience
all these things were done untouched by
human hands it was not like a bunch of
high priced computer guys sit down and
wrote this stuff these things were
evolved which is amazing and I think I
mentioned on the intro actually been
involved in two companies that use
genetic programming I was chairman of
analog design automation which used
genetic programming to improve human
designed analog circuits and you know
our lead investor was Intel we had all
the big chip companies as our customers
we ended up selling the company for a
nice price my bus they say so to
synopsis and then we had another company
called cielito design automation which
used genetic programming and and other
techniques to optimize manufacturer
ability of computer chips and again that
company was very successful and was sold
to Siemens not too long ago so there's
are some real world really hard problems
that GP has been applied to John do you
keep up on the state of the art and GP
and do you know of what's going on on
the cutting edge these days well I've
been staying closely involved with the
annual human competitive competition
which is now in its I think 20th year
and every every year they run a
competition where they give prizes or
human competitive things that have been
designed with any evolutionary
computation technique genetic algorithms
genetic programming or other techniques
the majority of the prizes have gone in
the genetic programming category but
there have been a whole string of
impressive results every year and if
people go to wwhen - competitive that
org they can look at the progression of
increasingly impressive things that have
won prizes over the last twenty or so
years cool could you call out a couple
that you were impressed by recently I
personally was very impressed with Lee
specters worked on quantum computer
circuits and moshi sippers repeated
winning a prizes both of them repeatedly
of won prizes in that competition in the
area of game playing but there's been
just a whole number of other ones I
don't mean to slide anybody else by
having mentioned those - ah very good
what an amazing idea you've had John and
how far it's gone and so now let's move
on to the third area of innovation and
this is the national popular vote
initiative could you start by telling us
about it that's kind of a high level
what the motivation was but then I'll
ask you some more questions we'll go
into some more detail well again that
goes back to my very busy career as a
graduate student at University of
Michigan in the 60s so very busy on
frankly everything but my thesis for
most of the years I was in Ann Arbor so
I was had this significant part-time job
of programming for the game company
while I was working on my thesis but of
course graduate students Lana now were
very occupied with playing games as any
previous graduate student well knows and
in the sixties a very complicated board
games were very much the rage the Avalon
Hill war games and an Avalon Hill had a
number of other complicated games
involving railroad switch yards and
there was diplomacy and risk and a whole
bunch of games
Stratego but we got interested in
creating our own game so it created a
game based on the electoral college
which was a topic of quite prominent
debate in the 60s so we had this game
that John Holland played with the
graduate students we had a computer
program that would run simultaneous with
playing the game creating different
statistical matrices so we could
evaluate the state of the play at each
stage and we would pretend to be
presidential campus campaigning for
president using the quarks and oddities
of the electoral college so this game
was called consensus which we actually
published commercially lost the money on
and sold 3,000 copies but this game was
sort of always in the back of my mind
how utterly ridiculous the electoral
college is as a method for choosing the
president and how subject it is to
manipulation and producing odd results
so in the 90s and 2000's particularly
2004 election it had become increasingly
clear that presidential campaigns had
concentrated only on a handful of states
when Kennedy ran in 60 he campaigned in
35 states and Nixon campaigned in all 50
when Kerry and Bush were campaigning in
2004 almost the entire campaign law
virtually the entire campaign was in a
dozen states but essentially the whole
campaign was in three stick and that's
because under the current system the
candidate who gets the most votes inside
each state gets all of the state's
electoral votes so if a state is 5% or
6% in one direction it's really out of
reach during a presidential three-month
campaign so if you're running for
president and you want to win you do all
your campaigning in the states that are
within one or two or three percent the
so-called swing states or battleground
state and this battleground that had
been fairly large in the 40s 50s and 60s
had shrunk by 2004 to just a handful of
states which is of course still the case
today and the result is not only
most of the people in United States are
politically irrelevant in the
presidential election in the general
election but you could also get
candidates elected president who didn't
get the most votes in all 50 states
which of course occurred in 2000 and
then more recently in 2016 and just in
general obviously every vote was not
equal and most voters were just
politically irrelevant so it turned out
I have lost a 25-cent bet when I was an
undergraduate to a pre-law student in
the dorm at Michigan I had claimed that
the winner-take-all rule was in the US
Constitution and the law student said no
no no it's not in the Constitution and I
did lose the bet and I still remember
that because he was right it turns out
the way we elect the president isn't
really in the Constitution it's in state
laws state by state that have adopted
these laws they reward all their
electoral votes to the candidate get the
most votes inside the state and I got to
talking with a lawyer friend of mine he
was a lawyer friend because when I was
in the lottery business in the 80s he
and I wrote lottery laws that we got
different legislators to pass which we
passed in several cases in California
Oregon Arizona through the initiative
process so he and I weren't quite aware
of the process of lobbying state
legislatures and passing laws by
initiative and we got to talking one day
at lunch and said why couldn't you elect
the president in a national popular vote
not by amending the Constitution but
just by changing these state
winner-take-all laws and we started
researching this and quickly discovered
that well not only was the pre-law
student right back in the early sixties
when he swindled me out of 25 cents but
it turns out that the way to do it is
with the states getting together with
what are called interstate compacts
these are legally binding contracts
among states
new things and usually a state enters an
interstate compact only because it gets
something and gives up something to
other states in fact an interstate
compact is a way of resolving a
prisoner's dilemma that is no state
would want to change its method of
electing the president from
winner-take-all to some other method
unless it got something in return and
particularly didn't reduce its own
influence so it turns out interstate
compact is a way to unravel a prisoner's
dilemma that might exist so we combined
the idea of the interstate compact with
the idea that the legislators had the
exclusive power to decide how the
president selected and created some
legislation which we introduced in a
book in 2006 and we started going around
to different states trying to get them
to pass this law and Maryland was the
first state to enact in 2007 so thank
you Jim for being a Maryland person and
being part of getting national popular
vote started and we went into this
organization national popular vote
started lobbying state legislators and
one by one we got legislators to start
passing this usually about one a year
until 2019 when we got four states in
one year and now we're in a place where
we have 15 states in the District of
Columbia with 196 electoral votes that
have passed this interstate compact and
it will go into effect when states
having half the electoral votes which is
270 out of 538 passed the same block and
we're working to get the remaining
states which would be we need states
with 74 more electoral votes to get to
to 7 ah yeah wow what an amazingly
audacious thing all starting from a game
and it's interesting I was another one
of those people that loved Avalon Hill
games back they started playing
yeah tactics too when I was 9 at a
friend's house and I actually bought
used the copy of stalingrad when I was
10 and became a hell of a good
stalingrad player and played many of the
rest
then even more humorously I later made a
small investment in the avalon hill
company which was publicly traded and i
added to it and added to it stock never
did well the company was horribly
unprofitable run very badly by a couple
of clowns who had bought it but I got
the meet Curt Schilling because it
turned out that he and I were the two
largest non insider shareholders and we
conspired together to try to buy the
company one time but didn't work out but
we ended up making some money when the
company was acquired by Hasbro I think
it was or one of the big game companies
but anyway a little interesting history
on games but now let's get back on the
popular vote could you explain a little
bit about what a state compact is you
kind of touched on it and then maybe
more specifically what's in this
proposed state compact well yes so let
me first connect the interstate compacts
with the lotteries because the reason we
thought of this is that in the mid-80s
lotto games were getting started with
state lotteries and lotto games offered
a very large prize as you know and some
of the smaller states have Maine New
Hampshire and Vermont because they had
so few people they couldn't run a lotto
game the way New York or New Jersey
could with a big multi-million dollar
prize so they got together and passed an
interstate compact creating the Tri
State lotto Commission and that's how I
became aware of interstate compact and
as it turned out my company scientific
games won the first contract to run a
lotto gate for the tri-state a lot of
commission that was our first contract
for a lotto game our specialty being
instant games but we were branching out
into a lot of games so I became aware of
the idea of an interstate compact and
also became aware of the fact that
Congress usually doesn't have to consent
to States entering into interstate
compacts now many times Congress does
have to consent but we had looked into
it as a legal matter because when we
were in the press of
bidding on the contract we were
scratching our head wondering whether
this tri-state lotto
Commission was a legal entity and
actually had any legal authority to run
this game or give us a contract and it
turns out that if the topic does not
threaten federal supremacy the states
can enter into a compact without
congressional consent and gambling was
considered something that did not
threaten federal supremacy because
Congress basically took the position
that as far as they were concerned
gambling is illegal and similarly
because the Constitution specifically
gives the state legislatures the power
to decide how to award their electoral
votes this is another area where an
interstate compact would not require
congressional consent not that we were
against having congressional consent but
obviously it's another step and we were
pleased to discover that at least based
on existing judicial precedents a
compact that involves some exclusive
state power doesn't require
congressional percent so to answer your
question Jim how does the compact work
it says basically Delaware which one of
the states that passed our bill in 2019
will give its three electoral votes to
the presidential candidate who gets the
most popular votes in all 50 states in
the District of Columbia that is
Delaware is throwing its three electors
into a pot of electors that's going to
go to the candidate who wins the
National popular vote
now of course Delaware would want to do
that alone that's the prisoner's dilemma
aspect it would only want to do that if
it knew it was going to change the
system to create a national popular vote
so the second operative Clause of our
compact is the compact doesn't take
effect until States having a majority of
the electoral votes enact the very same
law so when we get to states with 270
electoral votes there will be a group of
states that have passed the same law
saying they're going to give
all of their electors to the Candide who
gets the most votes in all 50 states
then that law goes into effect and you
have a national popular vote for
president because whoever gets the most
votes in all 50 states
is going to get at least 270 electoral
votes which is enough to become
president so you have a method by
changing state law of changing the way
the president is elected in all 50
states
very very very clever and you know we
did learn a little bit about the
prerogatives of the state to do what
they want with their electoral votes
during that Florida snafu in 2000 where
the Florida State Legislature was
threatening to just flat-out appoint
electors for George Bush you have either
the US Supreme Court of the Florida
Supreme Court ruled the result the other
way and constitutional lawyers that they
had a pretty good argument to make there
a few questions for you you list list
your website does 16 jurisdictions 15
states in the District of Columbia that
have enacted your multi-state compact
and as I'm looking down the list all of
them are either mostly Democratic or
Democratic leaning states or
jurisdictions any reason why that seems
to be the case well when we started in
those six George W Bush was still
president and Republicans generally
didn't support this heavily we would get
a few Republican votes then in 2008 as
he was leaving office we started getting
about a third of the Republicans in
state legislatures in roll calls to vote
for our bill because the bush 2000
election it was receiving from memory
and it correctly occurred to people that
this had nothing to do with the 2000
election but everything to do with
future elections and as a matter of
public policy it is not good that people
get into the White House who don't have
a strong popular base of support and
it's certainly not good that three out
of four states that are ignored
politically in the presidential election
so we went to a period then won Obama
was president when the Democratic
got less and less interested in passing
this bill first though we have already
gotten several democratic states
secondly there was a sort of arrogant
triumphalist mentality that had set in
on the Democratic side that Democrats
had a permanent block on the White House
and why changed the system since it
elected Obama now curiously 1989 the
phrase electoral college lock was
invented by a Republican bigsby who said
that the Republicans had a lock on the
electoral college because Reagan and
Bush had just been successful and Nixon
had won twice before that and this many
states had voted Republican the five out
of six times well the same completely
nonsensical arrogant belief settled in
on the Democratic side it was called the
blue wall theory that because states
with 242 electoral votes had voted six
times in a row the Democrats would
always win the White House well that
little wall of theory went out the
window just as quickly as the Republican
electoral college lock went out the
window as soon as the next election
arrived so we went through a period when
we started getting a lot of Republican
support passed the Oklahoma stun Atwoods
probably controlled the Arizona House
two-thirds of the Republicans sponsored
the bill and two-thirds of both parties
voted for it and 47 out of 56 Georgia
Senate members sponsored the bill in 16
and the only reason we became law in New
York was that the republican-controlled
Senate passed it so we went through a
period where Republican support was
increasing and then of course we had the
2016 election and then suddenly instead
of like a square-dance everybody changed
party lines and all of a sudden the
Republicans no longer thought that it
was important that every state matter
and be politically relevant and that
every vote would be equal and the candy
with the most votes to win and all of a
sudden the Democrats said oh my goodness
the electoral college is
apparently biased against us so we've
gone through this cycle of partisanship
and we're plotting along and you have to
just explain the issue one by one to the
7400 people who actually have a vote in
this matter
show the 7400 state legislators
interesting and of course was I was
fighting interesting you know how
short-term people's reactions are the
one you didn't mention it was the close
call in 2004 where Bush had like a three
million popular vote margin but if two
hundred thousand votes had switched in
Ohio John Kerry would have won the
electoral college with a significant
shortfall on the popular vote again on
the Democratic side so people forget all
about 2004 I guess because it didn't
happen but it was a close-run thing and
I'm with you that people who try to lock
in short-term advantage are not thinking
properly but they just had an idea I'm
gonna throw out to you I think I know
how you can get this thing passed by
both Democrats and Republicans are you
interested
well of course okay suppose you amend it
you got to get back everybody to amend
it and say that this will go into effect
twenty years after the 270 well it's a
practical matter that wouldn't get you
any votes it's an interesting idea and
but it doesn't change the way people
look at it at the moment you know the
2004 election wasn't the only near miss
Carter almost lost the election even
though he's ahead by 3 million votes
people forget Nixon in 68 just squeaked
by with a very tiny number of votes
switching and in a couple of states
would have made Humphrey the president
even though Nixon did win the national
popular vote and in 68 as similarly with
truman wilson's reelection in 1916 was a
matter of a switch of three thousand
votes in california
even though wilson was extremely far
ahead in the national popular vote so
the system we have is very quirky that's
why the game we had in the 60s was so
interesting
as it had so many quirky and frankly
ridiculous results that you can get out
of this winner-take-all system but
before wasn't was hardly unique that's a
very good point I don't know if you
remember this John but you sent me a
draft of your book when it was in
process and it was 2003 or 2004 and I
read it and we had a phone call I maybe
mailed you a few comments and I was
going back through my memory and I still
have those same three concerns that I
had then so let me run them by you and
get your reaction I'm sure these are not
the first time you've heard these
because you know you've been out there
being shot at by people for many many
years so I'm sure you've got good
answers but at the time these were my
gosh ins at least which is as you point
out there's been many many close
elections at the presidential level in
fact I recall after we had our
conversation I wrote a little simulator
to see how often very close elections
and the aggregate popular vote would
occur even assuming fairly large
variance at the state level and the
answer was a lot so what happens if we
do have a really really really close one
so close that if it were to have
happened at a state level we could
demand a recount
you know for instance in 1960 it was 0.1
percent of the popular vote in nineteen
sixty-eight point seven two thousand
point five you know most states have at
least some form of recanvassing at the
1% threshold and often at 0.5 percent
there's the ability to demand a recount
how in the world could we do a national
recount of a popular vote that was under
half a percent let's say particularly
when not all the states are involved in
the interstate compact well the reality
is you can't do a recount now in
presidential elections you recall there
was no recount in 2000 even though the
difference of the state level was 537
votes and 537 votes determined who was
President of the United States
there was no recount in Pennsylvania or
Michigan in 2016
simply because the claim is in 2000 the
candidate who was initially had went
into court and found a technicality and
ran the clock out and the key point is
there's a clock on this recount because
of the 20th amendment which move the
inauguration from March 4th to January
20th there's only 7 weeks between the
election and the inauguration and
there's actually only a few weeks in a
practical sense because it takes a
couple of weeks to create the first
count so the other practical
consideration is most state laws don't
actually work to let you have a retail
take Ohio which is intestinal
battleground state and turns out there's
a 15-day waiting period in their recount
law
well between November 4th and December
12th you just don't have 15 days to wait
to start the court proceedings after
you've spent two or three weeks with a
count so the first problem is
effectively there are no recounts
practically possible right now in
presidential elections secondly they
would be much less frequent and national
popular vote the threshold is not a
tenth of one percent the number of votes
changed in a recount is about 300 at the
state level and that's based on actual
statistics of the 28 recounts over the
last 20 years and the chance of a
recount is 1 in 200 so if we ran 200
presidential elections yes once in 800
years you would be close enough to
warrant a recount
these recounts that occur in some states
when there's a 1% gap our public
relations recounts they're designed to
is fill public confidence but 1% of
votes do not change in any recount at
least any recount that I'm aware of
certainly none in the last 20 years
where the average recap change in a
recount is 300 votes and we're 6 out of
7 Rica
simply reaffirm the previous results but
to answer your alternate question how
would you run a recount you you need a
national recount law and we wrote one
and put one on our book which is more
needed under the current system that
would be needed under national popular
vote because the current system creates
50 opportunities for recount every four
years whereas we would create only one
opportunity for recount or for years but
we do need a right to recount that's
unconditional and can't be brushed aside
with delaying tactics and self-serving
running out the clock which is what what
occurs now so recount is a messy area
all I would say is things would be
better under national popular vote
because there would be less probability
of having a recount in the first place
that seemed reasonable but if we did
have one early without the national
recount law we'd have a serious problem
well of course you would but the reality
is you have a serious problem now
because if there was a close vote
nationally remember there are 12 of the
50 states are closely divided
battleground states there would also be
probably 12 states that are closed and
you have recounts there that's a good
handling look you have to have our
national recount you'd have won almost
all the votes are counted in the first
12 hours that's how we get election
result by election night or election or
Wednesday morning so if they parallel
process that's not like 137 million
ballots are dumped on the desk of one
guy in Washington and he's told he has
to recount them votes would be recounted
the same way they are counted which is
at the local level in parallel by teams
in every locality in every state so I
wouldn't get too wrapped up over that
they're more lotto tickets sold on a
given week than there are balance and
the lotto tickets are issues with the
same sort of accuracy as credit card
transactions by the hundreds of millions
there's no big deal conducting a recount
because it would be conducted in
parallel okay that's a tolerable answer
so if it doesn't happen the next one I
think this one was when I was most
concerned at a time was what happens if
it's very close and that one of the
compact states you know that its own
popular vote went strongly the other way
and it decides to renege you know it's
at least strongly arguable that the US
Constitution gives state legislators
absolute discretion on how to allocate
electoral votes suppose the state
legislature meets between the Tuesday
election date in the meeting the
electoral college and by a legislative
vote says nope we're gonna renege and
here's our vote all nice and illegal
under our state constitution we renege
and we're appointing the electors for
the other guy and that that then breaks
the compact oh that's a total non
problem first of all the state
legislatures power to decide out
allocate their electoral votes is
substantial but it's limited by other
provisions of the Constitution notably
the fact that interstate compacts are
contracts and the Constitution prohibits
a state from impairing an obligation of
contract so it's really airtight
constitutional law that no state can get
out of an interstate compact except in
the manner that the compact itself
allows and our compact says if you try
to leave between July 20th and January
20th of a presidential year your
departure occurs after the inauguration
of the new president and there's been no
case where the Supreme Court's or any
Court has ever allowed any state to
wiggle out of any under state compact
ever and so I wouldn't worry about that
also there's a federal law on top of it
which requires that presidential
electors be selected based on laws in
place prior to election day so there's
also a statutory reason why that can't
happen and in a practical sense it can't
happen
because most state legislators are not
in session in that short period and even
if they were most state constitutions
only let a new law take effect 60 or 90
or a hundred days after it gets passed
so wouldn't even matter if there were no
impairments cause there were no federal
statute even if all the legislators were
in session most states could not pass a
law that would go into effect quickly
enough to renege even if it was possible
though of course
Florida actually was going down that
road to do so in the 2000 election well
actually they weren't what Florida was
doing was they were passing a resolution
saying that if the courts vacated the
results of the vote by the people on
November 3rd or whenever it was then the
legislature was reaffirming the choice
of the Republicans slate of presidential
electors but only if a court had done
that so if you actually look under the
hood of what was going on in Florida in
2000 they weren't coming in and saying
we have the power after election day to
override our own voters they does not
have that power because of the federal
statute I mentioned great that's good I
just learned something new there that
sounds pretty damn solid now we're
getting out of the kind of hard
machinery aspects and more - is it good
you know could a national popular vote
result in more polarization suppose you
know today the electoral college system
requires people to compete in some of
the more closely balanced States to win
you can't go too far afield and win in
Ohio or Wisconsin or Florida or
Pennsylvania we went to a national
popular vote system like John is
suggesting might not the result be for
the campaign's to try to really run up
the margins in the most polarized states
you know the California's the New York's
you know the Texas is etc rather than
having a campaign that's a
more towards you know the centrists
states well of course the way candidates
actually campaign inside the
battleground states is simply the same
way they would campaign nationally so
when you're running for president inside
Ohio which is a closely divided
battleground state of course you try to
run up the vote in the parts of Ohio
where your party is strong as that goes
without saying so that process already
exists you milk the areas where your
party is strong but remember both
parties are doing that simultaneously
and you go after the votes in the middle
in Ohio which are available to your
party and our related question is you
know would candidates campaign only in
the big cities for example which is one
we hear very often so we've looked at
how candidates actually campaign and the
way they actually campaign now inside a
battleground state remember inside a
battleground state every vote is equal
can date with the most votes wins that's
exactly the formula of national popular
vote every vote is equal candidate with
the most votes wins and inside Ohio 22%
of the state is outside the standard
metropolitan statistical areas the
so-called rural areas and they get 25
percent of the visits so for all
practical purses they get visits in
proportion to their population the big
cities the Cleveland Cincinnati Columbus
individually and as a group they get
exactly the percentage that their
population is and the metro areas get
the same percentage and the mid-sized
cities of which they're seven in Ohio
though Youngstown's and Dayton's etc
that also tracks population why is that
true because if you're running a
presidential campaign in a battleground
state you've got the most knowledgeable
professional advisors in the world
telling you that if every vote is equal
every vote is equal and it would be
insanity to campaign
otherwise and we've gone through and
mapped the appearances of candidates in
Florida and Ohio and of the dozen or so
battleground states and the candidates
do not hover around Miami or
Philadelphia or Cleveland or Denver or
Des Moines or Las Vegas they campaign
all over the state because that is the
way you have to campaign if you're gonna
win so a lot of this rhetoric about big
cities controlling elections or
polarization is really just that when
you actually look how candidates
campaign they are very rational and if
they're rational they have to follow the
the voters ah great answer that sounds
like you guys have done the work and you
have the data that shows that people do
act rationally and apply their level of
effort to where the voters are no doubt
seasoned by their estimate of how many
voters they have in an area they're not
gonna spend a lot of resources in an
area it's 90 percent for the other guy
but that sounds good sounds like you've
thought these up what are some other
objections that are out there that you
have answers for let me just give me two
two more objections that you regularly
hear that you feel like you've got good
answers for well we think we have good
answers 231 myth that we cover in our
book we actually cataloged all of the
things that different people have said
and we think we've got a good answer for
all of them but one of the ones that
comes up quite often is it's an argument
to call it federalism it's somehow an
uneasy feeling that some others are
going to upset the federal system and
you really have to look at it though we
do have a good system we divide power
between states and the national
government and that's not only allows
for innovation at the state level and
experimentation but it also prevents one
party from ever getting a foothold for
example suppose the Constitution said
that the states legislatures didn't
control how the president was elected
but Congress did that
be a fairly natural way of writing a
constitution and in fact that is the way
it's done in many countries because
there is no federal system with states
with meaningful amounts of power then
you'd have an election system where the
party and power would write the election
rules and anybody in power can think of
ways of changing the election rules to
keep themselves in power so you have a
dispersal of power well there's nothing
about how you elect presidential
electors whether you elect them by a
congressional district or state level or
national that in any way increases or
decreases the amount of power that state
government has or the national
government has so an argument we often
hear but it reflects sort of a natural
concern a legitimate concern but for
which is a good an argument is this is
not something that's changing the
structural amount of power that
different levels of government have say
way of changing the way you're counting
votes and we get a lot of that and I
think that's not really very convincing
okay you said you had one other one well
we have a hundred thirty-one other ones
all right yeah let me tell your people
actually I just clicked on that national
popular vote.com forward slash answering
- myths oh my god that I am law answered
and as you heard John he can slay these
objections right wow he blew me out of
the water so if you think you have an
objection to you know the national
popular vote interstate compact go to
there and we'll put that link up on our
website for the episode and see what he
says I suspect you might be well spanked
these guys have obviously done their
work whenever anybody proposes change
it's perfectly legitimate natural to try
to think of every possible objection or
thing that can go wrong and it's
perfectly normal that there be a hundred
and thirty one objections and if you're
proposing a change you need to have a
good answer for all or virtually all we
think we have good answers for all of
the objection and you have to make the
case the burden of proof
is on the people who want to change
things I love it that's what I'd call a
good faith way to argue you basically
let people bring forth the objections
and you knock them down one after the
other I wish more of our political
process worked that way well John I want
to thank you for a most interesting
interview I mean you've had just the
most amazing set of professional
experiences you know inventing a
significant cultural phenomenon the
scratch off lottery ticket invented one
of the more important intellectual
contributions in computer science and
genetic programming and now doing strong
work in changing how we elect our
president in a very clever way yet one
that seems sound without amending the
Constitution I gotta say you're an
inspiration well thank you Jim for
inviting me to be here today it's been
wonderful I've learned a thing or two
with that we'll wrap her up production
services and audio editing by Jared
Jane's consulting music by Tom Muller at
modern space music com